

Bogdan Toader

Research Interests

I am an applied mathematician interested in the broad fields of machine learning, optimisation, inverse problems and data science, and their application to imaging problems in science. My current focus is on algorithms used in cryogenic electron microscopy (cryo-EM), including both traditional iterative algorithms and approaches based on deep learning. Previously, I worked on algorithms for deconvolution with spatially varying point spread function arising in light-sheet microscopy and developed theory for the stability of the super-resolution problem with non-negative measures.

EMPLOYMENT

Sep 2021 – present Postdoctoral Research Associate, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut, USA.

Department of Statistics and Data Science and the Quantitative Biology Institute (QBio).

Research on algorithms for cryo-EM reconstruction.

Sep 2022 – Dec 2022 Visiting Researcher, UCLA, Los Angeles, California, USA.

Institute for Pure and Applied Mathematics.

Core participant of the IPAM Long Program on Computational Microscopy.

Jul 2019 – Jul 2021 Postdoctoral Research Associate, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK.

Cambridge Advanced Imaging Centre (CAIC).

Research on **deconvolution algorithms for light-sheet microscopy**, a project in collaboration with the Cambridge Image Analysis Group in the Department of Applied Mathematics and Theoretical Physics and MRC Laboratory of Molecular Biology.

EDUCATION

Oct 2018 - Mar Enrichment Student, Alan Turing Institute, London, UK.

2019 Six months placement at UK's national institute for data science and artificial intelligence.

2015 – 2020 PhD in Mathematics, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK.

Industrially Focused Mathematical Modelling (EPSRC Centre for Doctoral Training) in collaboration

with the National Physical Laboratory (NPL).

Thesis title Stability and perturbation analysis of non-negative super-resolution

Advisors Prof Jared Tanner, Dr Andrew Thompson

 $2009-2013 \quad \textbf{BSc (Hons) Computer Science and Mathematics with Industrial Experience}, \textit{University}$

of Manchester, Manchester, UK.

First class degree with final grade above 80%.

Publications

1. Methods for cryo-EM single particle reconstruction of macromolecules having continuous heterogeneity B. Toader, F. J. Sigworth, R. R. Lederman

Accepted in Journal of Molecular Biology, arXiv:2211.10744, 2023

2. Integrating molecular models into cryo-EM heterogeneity analysis using scalable high-resolution deep Gaussian mixture models

M. Chen, B. Toader, R. R. Lederman

Accepted in Journal of Molecular Biology, arXiv:2211.10518, 2023

3. Image reconstruction in light-sheet microscopy: spatially varying deconvolution and mixed noise B. Toader, J. Boulanger, Y. Korolev, M. O. Lenz, J. Manton, C.-B. Schönlieb, L. Mureşan

Journal of Mathematical Imaging and Vision, vol. 64, pp. 968-992, 2022

4. Sparse non-negative super-resolution – simplified and stabilised

A. Eftekhari, J. Tanner, A. Thompson, B. Toader, H. Tyagi

Applied and Computational Harmonic Analysis, vol. 50, pp. 216-280, 2021

5. The dual approach to non-negative super-resolution: impact on primal reconstruction accuracy

S. Chrétien, A. Thompson, B. Toader

2019 13th International conference on Sampling Theory and Applications (SampTA) proceedings pages 1-4, 2019

6. Global air transport complex network: multi-scale analysis

W. Guo, B. Toader, R. Feier, G. Mosquera, F. Ying, S. Oh, M. Williams, A. Krupp Springer Nature Applied Sciences (SNAS), vol. 1(7), 2019

7. Non-negative super-resolution is stable

A. Eftekhari, J. Tanner, A. Thompson, B. Toader, H. Tyagi 2018 IEEE Data Science Workshop, DSW 2018, proceedings pp. 100-104, 2018

PREPRINTS

8. On manifold learning in Plato's cave: remarks on manifold learning and physical phenomena

R. R. Lederman, B. Toader

Submitted, arXiv:2304.14248, 2023

9. The dual approach to non-negative super-resolution: perturbation analysis

S. Chrétien, A. Thompson, B. Toader Submitted, arXiv:2007.02708, 2020

AWARDS

- 2022 IPAM Long Program Housing and Travel Grant, University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) US
- 2018 Enrichment Placement Award, Alan Turing Institute London, UK
- 2018 Travel Award, SIAM UKIE Annual Meeting, Southampton, UK
- 2016 IMA Best Team Performance Prize, InFoMM Graduate Modelling Camp, Oxford, UK
- 2015 EPSRC InFoMM CDT Studentship, Oxford, UK
- 2010 Golden Anniversary Prize, University of Manchester, UK
- 2006–2009 Bronze Medal at the National Mathematical Olympiad, Romania in 2007, 2008 and 2009

Conference and seminar presentations

- Sep 2023 11th Applied Inverse Problems Conference, Göttingen, Germany mini-symposium presentation
- Feb 2023 SIAM Conference on Computational Science and Engineering (CSE23), Amsterdam, The Netherlands mini-symposium presentation
- Nov 2022 IPAM Seminar, UCLA, Los Angeles, US oral presentation
- Sep 2022 SIAM Conference on Mathematics of Data Science (MDS22), San Diego, US poster presentation
- $\begin{array}{ll} \text{May 2022} & \textit{PIMS Workshop on Mathematical and Computational Challenges in Cryo-EM}, \text{Vancouver}, \text{Canada} \\ & \text{invited presentation} \end{array}$
- March 2021 Focus on Microscopy 2021 Online Conference oral presentation
 - Sep 2020 Virtual 12th Light Sheet Fluorescence Microscopy Conference 2020 oral presentation
 - Jul 2020 SIAM Conference on Imaging Science (IS20), online poster presentation
 - Jan 2020 Quantitative BioImaging Conference (QBI 2020), Oxford, UK poster presentation
 - Aug 2019 International Conference on Continuous Optimization (ICCOPT 2019), Berlin, Germany oral presentation
 - Jul 2019 13th International Conference on Sampling Theory and Applications (SampTA 2019), Bordeaux, France oral presentation
 - Mar 2019 InFoMM Annual Meeting, Oxford, UK oral presentation
 - Feb 2019 InFoMM Group Meeting, Oxford, UK oral presentation
 - Jul 2018 Curves and Surfaces Conference, Arcachon, France oral presentation
 - Jun 2018 6th IMA Conference on Numerical Linear Algebra and Optimization, Birmingham, UK oral presentation
 - Jun 2018 2018 IEEE Data Science Workshop (DSW 2018), Lausanne, Switzerland poster presentation
 - Mar 2018 InFoMM Annual Meeting 2018, Oxford, UK oral presentation
 - ${\it Mar~2018~Numerical~Analysis~Seminar,~Oxford,~UK-oral~presentation}$
 - Feb 2018 Research Workshop on Optimization and Big Data, KAUST, Saudi Arabia poster presentation
 - Jan 2018 SIAM UKIE Annual Meeting, Southampton, UK poster presentation
 - May 2017 InFoMM Group Meeting, Oxford, UK oral presentation
 - Mar 2017 InFoMM Annual Meeting 2017, Oxford, UK poster presentation

OTHER RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Jul – Sep 2016 Deflating Magnetic Oscillations, Culham Centre for Fusion Energy, Abingdon, UK.

Used deflation to find multiple periodic solutions to a system of ODEs that describes the behaviour of plasma. In collaboration with Culham Centre for Fusion Energy.

Supervisors Prof Patrick Farrell (Oxford), Dr Wayne Arter (CCFE)

May – Jul 2016 Improved Source Reconstruction from Hydrophone Data, National Physical Laboratory, London, UK.

Analysed how compressed sensing can be applied to a problem on ship localisation from measurements of the sound in the shipping lane, proposed by the National Physical Laboratory. An extension of this work to grid-free compressed sensing applied to the same problem has been the focus of my PhD project for the following three years.

Supervisors Prof Jared Tanner (Oxford), Dr. Andrew Thompson (Oxford), Dr Peter Harris (NPL), Dr Stéphane Chrétien (NPL)

2012 - 2013 Formal Verification of Dynamical System, University of Manchester, UK.

Final year undergraduate thesis on using the automatic theorem prover MetiTarski to analyse equilibrium and stability properties of dynamical systems.

Supervisor Dr Eva Navarro-López

Industry Engagement

Dec 2019 Data Study Group, Alan Turing Institute, London, UK

Implemented deep learning based solution for image segmentation applied to brighfield microscopy data.

Jun 2019 Mathematics in Industry New Zealand Workshop, Auckland, New Zealand

Implemented optimal transport based solution for decomposing spectrum of cheese samples into different components (fat, protein etc.).

Jun 2018 142nd European Study Group with Industry, Palanga, Lithuania

Worked on predicting the sustainable income of loan applicants according to rules from the central bank.

Dec 2016 Data Study Group, Alan Turing Institute, London, UK

Implemented network model to solve an air traffic prediction problem proposed by Airbus.

May 2016 116th European Study Group With Industry, Durham, UK

Implemented mixed integer programming solution to problem on scheduling field trials proposed by Syngenta.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2020 – 2021 Numerical Analysis, University of Cambridge.

Supervisor for third year undergraduate students. Responsible with marking and running fortnightly supervisions for pairs of students from a number of Cambridge colleges.

2016 – 2018 Continuous Optimisation, University of Oxford.

Teaching assistant for fourth year undergraduate course. Responsible with marking weekly assignments and solving problems on the board during classes, to groups of up to 15 students. Ran revision classes independently to groups of 30 students.

2016–2018 Integer Programming, University of Oxford.

Teaching assistant for third year undergraduate course. Responsible with marking weekly assignments and solving problems on the board during classes, to groups of up to 15 students. Ran revision classes independently to groups of 30 students.

2016 – 2017 Computational Mathematics, University of Oxford.

Lab demonstrator for first year undergraduate Matlab classes. Presented new material in the form of live computer demo to groups of up to 20 students.

2010 – 2011 Peer Assisted Study Sessions Leader, University of Manchester.

Weekly sessions with first year undergraduate students, in groups of around 6, assisting them with basic mathematics and programming.

STUDENT SUPERVISION

2022 Mario E. Escabí Rivera, Yale Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship Program.

2021 **UK Graduate Modelling Camp**, Newton Gateway to Mathematics, Cambridge, UK. Proposed a modelling and computational problem and mentored a group of six PhD students on reaching a solution as a team.

OUTREACH

2017 – 2018 Lord Williams's School, Thame, Oxfordshire, UK.

Ran two outreach sessions (in 2017 and in 2018 respectively) aimed at pre-final year students about doing research in applied mathematics. Presented material on the mathematics of machine learning.

Peer Review

2017 – present I acted as a reviewer for Applied and Computational Harmonic Analysis, Information and Inference: a Journal of the IMA and SIAM Journal on Imaging Sciences.

Non-academic Employment

2013 – 2015 Technology Associate, Morgan Stanley, London, UK.

Worked in the Pricing Technology team for the Interest Rate Derivatives business, where I used Scala and Perl to build and improve the pricing tools used by quantitative analysts and traders.

Jun – Jul 2012 Summer Intership, Technology, Credit Suisse, London, UK.

Part of the team that maintains the Unix servers in the EMEA region. On top of handling daily requests from users, I improved my shell scripting skills.

2011 – 2012 Industrial Placement, Technology, Morgan Stanley, London, UK.

Worked as part of the Institutional Securities Group Technology division in one of the teams developing and supporting the equities trading systems. Acquired experience of working with large sets of data.

OTHER.

Languages Romanian (native), English (fluent)

Hobbies Climbing, running, gliding, hiking, skiing, guitar